Reader's Feast Bookstore records GLBTQ.2012.02
Central Connecticut State University, GLBTQ Archives
Reader's Feast Bookstore records
1983-2000
GLBTQ.2012.02
GLBTQ Archives
0.5 Linear feet
The Reader’s Feast was an independent bookstore opened in 1983 in Hartford, Connecticut’s West End. The two co-managers, Carolyn Gabel and Tollie Miller, were avid women’s rights and gay rights activists and wanted to start a community bookstore where books representing all different cultures were sold and the environment was comfortable and safe for everyone. They ran the bookstore for twelve years, moving on to other ventures in 1995. This collection includes advertisements, newspaper articles, correspondence, and other materials directly related to Reader’s Feast from 1983-1996.
Gabel, Carolyn
Miller, Tollie
Biographical/Historical note
The Readers Feast opened in 1983 at 529 Farmington Avenue in Hartford, Connecticut. As the first independent, progressive bookstore in the area, Readers Feast sold books ranging from traditional fiction, cookbooks and children’s books to the latest feminist, gay and lesbian, Spanish language and progressive political titles. Their café (opening a few months later) had gourmet menu featuring light lunches and dinners, home-baked desserts and freshly brewed coffee, cappuccino, and espresso.
Thirty local people pooled their resources to invest in the bookstore including several professors from the University Of Connecticut School Of Social Work, attorneys from the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, community organizers from local groups, an artist and a gourmet cook. Carolyn Gabel, president and co-manager, was a former professor at the UCONN School of Social Work and Tollie Miller, co-manager and investor, were the owners for 12 years. Their goal was to create a community resource with books that represent different points of view and cultural perspectives and a safe, comfortable space for all kinds of people. Small events also occurred at the store such as readings, musical performances, small theatre presentation, and political meetings or talks. The arrival of the large national bookstore chain’s resulted in reduced sales. The struggle to run the bookstore during this difficult period resulted in Carolyn and Tollie stepping down in 1995. Under the new management of Barbara Mase, Roberta Collins, and Valerie de Palma, the bookstore continued to operate until 2007.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of subject files, records of the bookstore, correspondence, notes, flyers, printed materials, and photographs, which illustrate activities of the bookstore..
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for research.
Related Archival Materials note
An oral history interview of Carolyn Gabel-Brett is available within the Digital Collections of the GLTBQ Archives. The Carolyn Gabel-Brett collection located within the GLTBQ Archives at the Elihu Burritt Library has additional material connected to Reader's Feast.
Feminism -- United States -- History; Feminism -- United States -- Societies, etc; Independent bookstores -- United States; Small business -- Connecticut; Women -- America -- History; Women -- Connecticut -- Hartford
- American Bookseller’ Association- Letter and certificate commemorating ten year anniversary, August 31, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Benefit for Liberation Struggle in South Africa- Letter, September 20, 1985, volunteer list, agenda. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Charter Oak Celebrates Reader’s Feast- Program., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Field Trip to Reader’s Feast- 14 photographs of school children’s visit, February, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Gay Pride Day, Reader’s Feast, Float/Booth in Park- photographs, June 1992. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Haymarket People’ Fund- Correspondence regarding grant, August 28, 1984. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Grand Opening Celebration- Flyer, November 26, 1983. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- “I Love the Reader’s Feast” bumper sticker. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Independent versus Chains Bookstore Battle- Articles, advice sheets for small bookstores, registration forms for networking activities, newsletters, articles about Huntington’s Bookstore., 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Kitchen Staff Reader’s Feast- 5 photographs., 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- (Leap) Legislative Electoral Action Program, 1995 Annual Dinner Celebration- invitation, program book, November 17, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Malaprop’s Bookstore, The Birth of the Independent, Summer., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Reader’s Feast- Advertisements., 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Reader’s Feast- Anniversary Celebrations- Flyers., 1985-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Reader’s Feast- Cafe Menus (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Reader’s Feast- Articles., 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Reader’s Feast- Beginnings- News release, opening celebration flyer, article., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Reader’s Feast Calendar of Events., 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Reader’s Feast Calendar of Events, January-March., 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Reader’s Feast Calendar of Events, April-June., 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Reader’s Feast Calendar of Events, July-September., 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Reader’s Feast Calendar of Events, October-December., 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Reader’s Feast Community Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Reader’s Feast- Grand Opening photographs., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Reader’s Feast Order Forms., 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Reader’s Feast Song, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Reader’s Feast-41 photographs (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Student artwork exhibited in Reader’s Feast- 20 drawings (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Reader’s Feast 10th Anniversary- Event plans, articles, advertisements, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Reader’s Feast 12th Anniversary- Flyers., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Postcards [3] To Tollie Miller from Carol, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Reader’s Feast Changes Owners- Articles, letters to Tollie and Carolyn from customers., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Reader's Feast - Agreement of Sale, August 9, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Reader's Feast - Feminist Bookstore network pladge list and catalog, correspondence, clippings, notes, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Reader's Feast - correspondence, membership list, clippings, financial information., 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Reader's Feast - mailing list., 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reader's Feast - photographs, correspondence,notes., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reader's Feast - t-shirt with bookstore logo. (Box 2, Folder 6)